join me and come and learn how to knit
the magic loop technique
it uses long circular needles and it's
great fun
let's get started right so let's
get started with magic loop the reason
we use magic loop
is so that we can knit in a small circle
so if you've got to make a little bit of
a toy
or maybe a sleeve or a sock or something
like that
you can use a magic loop using large
sort of long
circular needles rather than using
double pointed needles where you need
sort of four or five
and you knit from needle to needle now
some people prefer double pointed
needles
and that's wonderful or you can try
magic loop
which i personally think is easier
but you have as long a cable as you like
so
the longer the better it is easier if
you've got a longer cable
i've got 16 stitches here that i've cast
on
it doesn't matter how you cast on
because it be down to the pattern that
you're working on or
or or anything like that it doesn't
really matter how you cast on
unless it's a stretchy thing but that's
a whole other story so
first thing we do is we separate the
stitches on the needle we cut them in
half
and i've got 16 stitches here so i'm
going to do two four
six eight slide them so that they're on
to the beginning of the cable
which is here then i'm going to put that
needle down i'm just going to
bend the cable and pull it
through so that
the other eight stitches slide
nicely onto the other needle
so you've got this in it this is our
setup
for any kind of magic loop knitting
you've got half the stitches sitting on
the back needle attached
to the working yarn and that's the one
attached to the ball
the cable is over here on your left hand
side
and the tips of the needles are on the
right hand side
the working yarn should always be
on the back needle and one of the
reasons for that is that as you knit
it will make sure that the purl bumps
are inside
and the stocking stitch nice front knit
stitch is on the outside
whenever you knit just a normal knit
stitch
in circular knitting you produce
stocking stitch or stocking hat
and so always make sure that the working
yarn is at the back
so to start knitting and to join this
into a circle
what we do is we bring this back needle
round to the front and we knit these
stitches so i'm just going to pop this
working yarn out the way over there for
a minute
and then slide the back needle out
bring it round to the front then grab
hold of your working yarn
and then we're going to make sure
that nothing's twisted so nothing's
twisted there
start knitting pull that right out the
first stitch
and when you knit the first stitch
you're also connecting these two
together to make a circle so try and
keep that one quite nice and tight
and then knit the rest of the stitches
on the needle and you see how the cable
has kind of got itself into a bit of a
bow
that's right that's perfectly fine
that's normal
so you knit the stitches
and then you turn the work
put the working yarn at the back pull
this cable through where's my tail there
and push the stitches onto the front
needle
so we've got back to that same setup
working yarn at the back
and we're going to knit these stitches
at the front you pull the back needle
around
grab the working yarn
a bit of a bendy old cable that one
knit whoops
knit the stitches on the front needle
okay
splitting the yarn look at that there we
are
and then when you've knitted that row
we turn the work around and it's best to
just let the other needle drop
pull the cable
push your needle through the front
stitches
sometimes that's a little bit tight when
it's the first couple of rows
and there you are back at the same
situation you've got
stitches on the front stitches on the
back working yarn
sitting at the back there so i'm going
to pull the back needle
around to the front pick up the working
yarn
and knit the
stitches of the front needle
then i'm going to turn it make sure you
keep the working yarn at the back
push this cable or pull it
through the stitches and push them onto
the needle at the front
so you've got the same set up
working yarn at the back pull the back
needle
around to the front pick up your working
yarn
and knit
and let's do this a few more times nice
and slowly and then we can see
you can start to see see this little
tube appearing
as we're knitting around in a circle
pull that tail there so i'm going to
turn it
slide the working yarn that's sorry
slide the cable through the stitches
and onto the needle like that
working yarn at the back bring the back
needle
forward pick up your working yarn
and knit now you might find
the first few rows as with any project
always look a bit scrappy until you get
going
you might find that where you've firstly
joined up your
circle that it might have a little you
might end up with a little bit of a gap
or something
don't ever worry about that because you
have this tail and you can put a little
stitch in if you need to
so we'll turn take the working yarn at
the back
pull this cable through
slide the stitches onto the front needle
there we go pull the back needle around
grab your working yarn and knit
this is a technique like i was saying
earlier you definitely can use with
socks
so i'm just going to do that again now
let's twist it around
and as ever same setup
working yarn at the back pull the cable
through
push the needle through the stitches so
you're ending up with the same situation
every time you're coming back to that
pull the back needle forward
and knit
um but it's good for sleeves especially
if you're doing little sleeves like baby
things
or toys around it goes
working yarn at the back pull the cable
through
and you can see that this starts to get
easier
when you've got a few rows going because
you can kind of see it more clearly
working yarn sitting at the back pull
the front needle through
grab the working yarn and then knit
so let's have a look at what we've got
here
i pull my needle through so we can see
it on the
needles next to each other this is the
setup
that you're looking for the whole way
through the needles are sitting next to
each other just like they were at the
start
the cables are on the left the working
yarn attached to the ball
is at the back on the back needle and
the reason that that's important
is that when you knit knitting
in the round it creates a lovely
stocking stitch
and you get the knit stitches on one
side and the purl stitches
in the inside and
by having the working yarn at the back
that makes sure that it's that right way
around
so that you can see the knitting coming
through
and so you just keep going until you
reach the point you need to reach
and cast off or join it something else
or but just make sure you always have
that
set up half the stitches on each needle
you keep the working yarn at the back
and you're always working on
the front stitches so that
is how we do the magic loop
so that is how we knit the magic loop
technique it's so fantastic you can use
it for anything
long cables are the way forward so if
you enjoyed that leave me a comment and
tell me all about it
tell me what you're going to knit with
magic loop and don't forget to subscribe
for more fantastic crafting videos
happinessing